<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sleep | Thought Stuff]]></title>
  <link href="http://steveparrington.github.io/blog/categories/sleep/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://steveparrington.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-29T12:58:29+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://steveparrington.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steve Parrington]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I Did to Fix My Sleep]]></title>
    <link href="http://steveparrington.github.io/blog/2017/01/28/what-i-did-to-fix-my-sleep/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-28T23:57:10+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://steveparrington.github.io/blog/2017/01/28/what-i-did-to-fix-my-sleep</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>University for me will always be remembered as a lost opportunity. That&rsquo;s not to say
I didn&rsquo;t get a lot out of my time there, I learnt a lot of things - both about myself and
about Computer Science. But I&rsquo;m almost certain I was capable of more than I achieved and
that ultimately the thing that let me down the most was a catastrophic sleep schedule.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d go to bed at 4am because that was when I felt tired, I faced the choice of either forcing
myself out of bed to go to lectures while heavily sleep deprived, or missing out on the education that
I was paying for to catch up on sleep. I&rsquo;d eat at odd times of day, I consumed way too
much caffeine to counteract the effects of sleep deprivation which only made it worse in the long
term. I became depressed, my grades were terrible and so began 5 years of not being able to
remember when I was last happy.</p>

<p>I went to see doctors and I read books and scoured the internet for anything that I could do to
improve my situation. The problem was that the solutions felt like too much of an imposition and
in my depressed state I lacked the will to try them. Fast-forward 5 years, I&rsquo;m a software developer
working in London, I&rsquo;m doing ok but I&rsquo;m miserable, I contemplate suicide as a way out but thankfully
reject it. It became clear to me that if I was ever going to be happy again, I needed to fix my sleep.</p>

<p>Sleep as it turns out is essential for cognition. A <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1739867/">study from the University of New South Wales</a>
compared the effects of sleep deprivation to alcohol intoxication and found that 17-19 hours without
sleep was equivalent to a blood alcohol concentration (BAC) of 0.05%! I used a BAC calculator to
see how that mapped on to actual drinks and found I&rsquo;d have to drink 6 16oz beers over 3 hours
to match that level of sleep deprivation. There&rsquo;s a vast amount of evidence to support the idea
that we need enough sleep to function - as anyone who has suffered difficulties with their
sleep knows all too well.</p>

<p>A frustrating aspect of my struggle to get enough sleep was that people who had no sleep problems
at all would declare that I just needed to go to bed earlier and all would be well. I&rsquo;d liken this
to telling someone with depression to just cheer up, it&rsquo;s just not that simple. It turns out that
our bodies have a variety of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circadian_clock">internal clocks</a> that coordinate our biology with the day-night cycle.
These are called circadian clocks - and the rhythms they control influence everything from our
core body temperature to the production of hormones to when we can fall asleep.</p>

<p>Clocks are never perfect, they&rsquo;re either a bit too fast or a bit too slow - because of this it&rsquo;s
important to be able to adjust them otherwise they gradually get out of sync with the rest of the
world. Our circadian clocks are no different, they&rsquo;re adjusted by external environmental factors
called &ldquo;zeitgebers&rdquo; (German for &ldquo;time-giver&rdquo;). These include light, temperature and even when we eat.</p>

<p>A lot of people know about the negative impact that screen use late at night has on our sleep,
this is because the light from the screen is making our body think it&rsquo;s still daytime and so the
biological conditions necessary for sleep are delayed. What a lot of people don&rsquo;t know is that some
people&rsquo;s sleep phase (the period of the day when they&rsquo;re most likely to sleep) is delayed significantly
by almost all artificial lighting. For these people - and I appear to be among them, the 21st century
is a place where we do not belong, we are maladapted for this environment. Fortunately for me, there was
no end of information on the topic online and I found very effective tools to take control of my circadian
rhythms. Unsurprisingly, this is done by manipulating the zeitgebers that affect our circadian clocks.</p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer: This is the stuff that worked for me, with my specific sleep problems. I sincerely hope
that you find these useful, but there&rsquo;s no guarantee. Also go and see your doctor, they can help.</strong></p>

<h2><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_therapy">Dark Therapy</a></h2>

<p>This is by far the most extreme intervention I made - it is also the most effective and when combined
with bright light therapy (described below) it can fix my sleep schedule in about 3 days, without the
bright light therapy it can take as long as 2 weeks. It&rsquo;s an incredibly simple intervention, I lie in
almost total darkness for some period before sleep, the idea being that it will prevent the delaying of
my sleep phase. I used to need to do it for 90 minutes every evening -
a massive amount of my free time, but it proved to be worth the trade. If you&rsquo;re desperate enough to do
this (as I was) there are some things you should know.</p>

<ul>
<li>Doing this every evening consistently is very difficult to keep up, for me, failure is inevitable.
Don&rsquo;t aim for perfection, aim for better than where you are now.</li>
<li>Podcasts, audiobooks and music will keep you sane.</li>
</ul>


<h2><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Light_therapy">Light Therapy</a></h2>

<p>Just as dark therapy is all about telling your body when it is night, light therapy is about
letting it know that morning has arrived. Essentially your eyes need to receive a lot of bright light
shortly after waking up. Standard indoor lighting will not do for this purpose - the cheapest way to
get the light you need is to go outside for a while after waking up (assuming the sun has risen).
If you&rsquo;re like me you&rsquo;ll find that this makes it a lot easier to get up in the morning - I normally
wake up before my alarm if I&rsquo;ve been doing it for a few days. This is because it advances the sleep
phase. As with the dark therapy, I have some tips.</p>

<ul>
<li>In the winter it can be difficult to get the required amount of light in the mornings, you can
make sure you get enough light by buying a SAD lamp, or if you don&rsquo;t want to have to sit in the
same place you can get a light visor (I have <a href="http://re-timer.com/">this one</a>) which means I can get my light while doing
my morning routine.</li>
<li>Try and do this as soon after waking up as possible, the advancing effect on the sleep phase diminishes
as the day progresses.</li>
</ul>


<h2><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_therapy#Virtual_darkness">Blue Blocking Goggles</a></h2>

<p>For me this is a less effective version of dark therapy - but it allows you to have a mostly normal
evening. All this involves is wearing some goggles with lenses that filter out light towards the blue
end of the spectrum. Blue light has a much more pronounced delaying effect than the other parts of the
spectrum, this is the idea behind software like <a href="https://justgetflux.com/">f.lux</a>, it tints your screen to be orange, reducing the
amount of blue light you see.</p>

<p>Personally I&rsquo;ve found that I still experienced some delaying
of my sleep phase while using these, but they&rsquo;re better than no intervention at all.
My current goggles have orange lenses, meaning they filter out blue light and some green light, but
I recently read that the green part of the spectrum has a delaying effect as well. My next
experiment is to acquire some goggles that block out both blue and green (red lenses) and see how
effective they are. I&rsquo;ll try to follow up with another post on how it goes.</p>

<ul>
<li>Most goggles that are available do not look fashionable, they&rsquo;re pretty much lab goggles.
I recently found out about <a href="https://www.carbonshade.com/">carbonshade</a>, they sell blue and green blocking glasses that don&rsquo;t look
terrible - worthwhile if you&rsquo;re put off by wearing goggles.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ve found that wearing the goggles and drinking green tea (see below) combine in a way that means
my dark therapy sessions only need to be 30 minutes long making them much more manageable.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Green Tea</h2>

<p>This is probably the most questionable thing I do in terms of the evidence available to support it.
The crux of it is that you <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22214254">need to get more L-Theanine in your diet</a> and it just so happens green
tea is full of the stuff. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theanine#Pharmacodynamics">L-Theanine has been shown to increase amounts of the neurotransmitter GABA in the brain</a>.
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma-Aminobutyric_acid#Pharmacology">GABA enhances catabolism of serotonin into N-acetylserotonin in rats</a>, this is
significant because N-acetylserotonin is a precursor to melatonin, the sleep hormone whose production
is suppressed by light. It is therefore speculated that GABA has a regulatory effect on sleep.</p>

<p>My personal experience with drinking 3 cups of green tea a day has been that I fall asleep more easily,
usually having better sleep quality. My self assessment is problematic scientifically for a number of reasons.
A data set of one does not count for very much, I could be biased and so my desire to see an improvement
means I&rsquo;ve deluded myself into thinking there is one. It&rsquo;s also the case that as humans age their typical
sleep phase gets earlier, I could have potentially improved independently of the green tea. I speculate that
this is not the case as it is generally agreed that sleep quality diminishes with age - and when I stop
drinking green tea I perceive a reduction in sleep quality.</p>

<ul>
<li>You don&rsquo;t have to drink green tea, you could take an L-Theanine supplement, or use some other
dietary source.</li>
<li>If you do use green tea make sure to brew it for long enough, just dipping the tea bag in water
won&rsquo;t extract the L-Theanine!</li>
<li>This combines very well with both blue blocking goggles and dark therapy.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Additional Things</h2>

<ul>
<li>Try to make your room as dark as possible, get a blackout curtain and cover up the charging lights
from your devices.</li>
<li>Try to regulate the temperature of your bedroom, 18 degrees celsius is a common recommendation.</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t consume caffeine from late afternoon onwards.</li>
</ul>


<p>And that&rsquo;s pretty much everything I do to manage my sleep. The results have been remarkable, I&rsquo;ve
beaten my depression and I&rsquo;ve been mostly happy for quite some time. I&rsquo;ve been more productive at
work and I&rsquo;m enjoying my life far more. I hope you can gain some value from what I&rsquo;ve shared - and
if there are caffeine fueled students out there reading this at 4am, turn out the lights, put on
a podcast and go to bed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
