<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Goals | Thought Stuff]]></title>
  <link href="http://steveparrington.github.io/blog/categories/goals/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://steveparrington.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-06-04T17:01:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://steveparrington.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steve Parrington]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Goals for 2017]]></title>
    <link href="http://steveparrington.github.io/blog/2017/02/04/goals-for-2017/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-04T14:17:04+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://steveparrington.github.io/blog/2017/02/04/goals-for-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every year at the end of December I tend to think a lot about how the previous 12 months
went and think up some goals for the coming year. Some may snort derisively at this, as
effectively I&rsquo;m making a bunch of New Year&rsquo;s resolutions and for people as a whole resolutions
don&rsquo;t seem to actually work. Personally I find the Christmas/New Year period ideal for thinking
about what I want to improve about myself, I always take time off work so it&rsquo;s ideal for
deciding upon some fresh goals.</p>

<p>Now of course it is February 2017, so as well as telling you about my goals I&rsquo;ll also discuss the
progress I made on them in January!</p>

<h2>1. Achieve a body weight of 110kg</h2>

<p>I carried this goal over from 2016 as I didn&rsquo;t achieve it, that&rsquo;s not to say I made no progress
though. I started 2016 weighing 143.5kg and I ended it weighing 136kg for a total loss of 7.5kg.
Safe to say there were ups and downs, but I proved something significant in 2016, which is that
I was able to lose weight and for the most part keep it off, even if it wasn&rsquo;t the amount that
I wanted. In 2017 I want to repeat that success - and hopefully dramatically surpass it.</p>

<p>My approach to weight loss differs from the approach most people take, most people resolve to
eat less food and get more exercise in order to shed body weight. I also strive to do this, but
I start from a very different place - my mind.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve practiced mindfulness meditation on and off for a few years, I was first interested in it
when I found out about a <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3191261/">study that showed training in mindfulness was more effective in helping
smokers quit than the American Lung Association&rsquo;s &ldquo;Freedom From Smoking&rdquo; treatment</a>.</p>

<p>It seemed a reasonable conclusion that if mindfulness could help with cigarette addiction it could
also help me train myself to eat less. I successfully employed mindfulness in the latter half of 2014
to help me achieve a 126kg body weight. I ended up gaining all of the weight back in 2015 as I felt
forced to change my priority to my sleep. With my sleep problems largely well managed, my focus on
weight loss resumed in 2016.</p>

<p>My approach is to meditate for 20 minutes every day combined with mindful eating of my evening meals.
Mindful eating is effectively meditation where you focus on the food you&rsquo;re eating rather than on
the breath, but it has other benefits beyond mindfulness practice. I find it useful for changing
the relationship I have with food. I&rsquo;ve picked up some bad habits where I mindlessly eat
while watching TV, barely paying attention to the weight I&rsquo;m piling on with every mouthful. Mindful
eating challenges that habit by having me pay close attention to every bite. It also encourages eating
meals slowly, which almost always results in me feeling satiated by the end of the meal.</p>

<p>My progress in January on this goal has been solid, I weigh 133.7kg, so I&rsquo;ve lost 2.3kg, hopefully
I can keep the pace up, but inevitably there will be stumbles where I gain a small amount back. The
key is resuming my routine quickly after I go off the rails.</p>

<h2>2. Achieve a resting heart rate below 60 beats per minute</h2>

<p>Cardiovascular health is probably the key health concern in my life at present, high blood pressure
runs in the family along with risks of heart disease and stroke. I hardly stack the deck in my favour
by carrying so much extra weight, but I can improve my health independently of my success in weight loss
through exercise. A reasonable measurement of cardiovascular fitness is resting heart rate, so I started
to measure it at the end of 2016 and the results were not good. It was showing a resting heart rate in
the 90s, at the high end of the normal range. So I resolved to start exercising to bring my resting heart
rate down.</p>

<p>I set a goal to get it below 80bpm. I achieved that goal about a week after starting to exercise, so I changed my goal again to 70bpm.
As of the end of January my resting heart rate for the last 5 days has been between 67-69bpm. Clearly I
didn&rsquo;t realise just how quick the response to exercise would be, I&rsquo;ve set a much more ambitious goal of
60bpm, we shall see if I have to move the goalposts yet again.</p>

<p>My routine is a fairly simple one, I modified my commute in order to force myself to walk more, by designing
movement into my every day life I walk at least 8000 steps on a workday. I still have active exercise sessions,
but I keep them short and intense, I alternate between interval training on a rowing machine on one day and
circuit training with bodyweight exercises like squats and press ups on the other. Thus far I&rsquo;ve found this
approach to be more sustainable than ones I&rsquo;ve attempted before. By acknowledging that I&rsquo;m not aiming to be
an athlete or a sportsman I&rsquo;m able to cut the amount of time I spend exercising but still get health benefits.</p>

<h2>3. Go to at least 3 music gigs</h2>

<p>I decided on this goal because I thought my life was a bit boring, I had my routine and I stuck to it, but
there&rsquo;s so much to do in London and I was missing out. I&rsquo;d always been put off going to gigs because I
wrongly assumed it would be a similar experience to going clubbing (I hate night clubs), it turns out I
really enjoy gigs, so this is my attempt to force myself to go to more.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve got tickets booked for 2 gigs so far this year, Iron Maiden and Primus, so I&rsquo;m already most of the way
there to achieving this goal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
